Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (II) 1791-1920
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (II), 1791-1920.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 B855
941 items.
Papers, 1791-1920, of the Brown, Coalter and Tucker families. Includes correspondence, of Frances Bland (Coalter) Brown with Margaret W. Barnes, members of the Braxton family, Henry Peronneau Brown, Fanny T. Bryan, John Coalter, St. George Tucker Coalter and members of the Morton family.
Braxton family,; Brown family,; Bryant family,; Coulter family,; Morton family,; Tomlinson family,; Tucker family,; Margaret W. Barnes,; Frances Bland Coalter Brown,; Henry Peronneau Brown,; Fanny T Bryan,; John Coalter,; St. George Tucker Coalter,; Maria Rind Coalter.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 941 items, 11/15/1950.
Biographical/Historical Information
Note: The following subscripts are genealogical citations separating generations within the same family.
A more extensive biography on the Brown, Coalter and Tucker families can be found by accessing the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I), Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
Coalter Family
John Coalter 1(1769-1838), was born in 1769 to parents Michael Coalter and Elizabeth Moore. He held the postion of tutor to the children of St. George Tucker (1752-1827), and Frances (Bland) Randolph Tucker (d.1788). A move to Williamsburg, allowed him to receive a law degree from the College of William and Mary under Bp. James Madison and George Wythe. A year later he married Maria Rind, the orphaned daughter of a Williamsburg printer, who had been serving as governess for the Tucker children. Coalter's first two wives died in chilbirth, Maria Rind Coalter in 1792; and Margaret Davenport of Williamsburg in 1795. Ann Frances Bland Tucker (1785-1813), daughter of St. George Tucker, was taken as his third wife in 1802. She later bore him his only three children, Frances Lelia Coalter (1803-1822), Elizabeth Tucker Coalter Bryan (1805-1853), and St. George Tucker Coalter (1809-1839). In 1822, Coalter took his fourth wife, the widow Hannah (Jones) Williamson.
Elizabeth Tucker Coalter 2(1805-1853), married John Randolph Bryan (godson of John Randolph of Roanoke). They had nine children; John Coalter Bryan (1831-1853), Delia Bryan, (d. 1833), Frances Tucker Bryan (b. 1835), Randolph Bryan (b. 1837), Georgia Screven Bryan (b. 1839), St. George Tucker Bryan (b. 1843), Joseph Bryan (b. 1847), Thomas Forman Bryan (1848-1851), Corbin Braxton Bryan (b. 1852).
St. George Tucker Coalter 2(1809-1839), married Judith Harrison Tomlin (1808-1859). They had six children; Walker Tomlin Coalter (1830-1831); John Coalter (1831- 1883); Henry Tucker (1833-1870); Ann Frances Bland Coalter (1835-1894), who married Henry Peronneau Brown (1832-1894), in 1858; Virginia Braxton Coalter (b. 1837), who married William. P. Braxton in 1855; and St. George Tucker Coalter (b. 1839), who married Amelia Downy in 1862 and Charlotte (Downy) Terrill in 1868.
Brown Family
Capt. Henry Brown 1(1760-1841), married Frances Thompson (1775-1822). Their children included Henry Brown, Jr. (1797-1836), who married Eleanor Tucker; Samuel T. Brown, who married Lissie Huger; Locky [Lockie] T. Brown (b. 1827), who married Alexander Irvine; Frances Brown, who married Edwin Robinson; Alice Brown, who married William M. Worthington; and John Thompson Brown (1802-1836), who married Mary E. Willcox.
John Thompson Brown 2(1802-1836) and Mary Willcox had three children; Henry Peronneau Brown (1832- 1894), who married France Bland Coalter (1835-1894); John Willcox Brown (b. 1833); and Col. John Thompson Brown, II (1835-1864).
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1791-1920, of the Brown, Coalter and Tucker families. Includes correspondence, of Frances Bland (Coalter) Brown with Margaret W. Barnes, members of the Braxton family, Henry Peronneau Brown, Fanny T. Bryan, John Coalter, St. George Tucker Coalter and members of the Morton family.
Also includes additional correspondences of members of the Brown, Coalter, Braxton, Tomlin and Bryan families including a letter, 29 April 1791, from Maria Rind to John Coalter as well as notes, accounts and newspaper clippings concerning the Brown family.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 4 series; series 1 contains letters; series 2 contains photographs; series 3 contains various printed material; and series 4 contains newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
The letters in series 1 is arranged alphabetically by author. The rest of the series is arranged chronologically by date.
Additional Separated and Related Material
Related Material
There are two collections within the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary that Relate to this Collection. They include, the Barnes Family Papers, and the Tucker-Coleman Papers.
Barnes Family Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Barnes Family Papers, 1797-1926, 1818-1875. 247 items. Collection number: Mss. 39.1 B26
Correspondence, chiefly 1820-1875, of Newman Williamson Barnes and his wife Margaret W.(Tomlin) Barnes of Richmond, Virginia and "Greenfield," Culpeper County, Virginia. Letters concern life in Falmouth, Virginia and also concern Fredericksburg, Virginia. Correspondents are members of the Braxton, Coalter, Tomlin and Oliver families.
Tucker-Coleman Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Tucker-Coleman Papers, 1664-1945, 1770-1907. 30,000 items. Collection number: Mss. 40 T79
Papers, primarily 1770-1907, of the Tucker and Coleman families of Williamsburg, Winchester, Lexington, Staunton and Richmond, including papers of St. George Tucker (1752-1827), Nathaniel Beverley Tucker (1784-1851), Henry St. George Tucker (1780-1848), Ann Frances Bland (Tucker) Coalter (1779-1813), John Coalter (1769-1838), John Randolph of Roanoke, and Cynthia Beverley Tucker Washington Coleman (1832-1908) as well as other family members.
Separated Material
Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I), Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I), 1780-1929. 3,433 items. Collection number: Mss. 65 B85
Papers, 1780-1929, of the Brown, Coalter and Tucker families including the papers of John Coalter (1769- 1838),John Thompson Brown (1802-1836). Among the correspondents are Maria (Rind) Coalter, St. George Tucker, William Munford, Frances Bland (Tucker) Coalter, St. George Tucker Coalter, Frances Bland (Coalter) Brown, the Rev. Moses D. Hoge, and Henry Peronneau Brown.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Braxton family.; Brown family.; Bryant family.; Coalter family.; Coulter family.; Morton family.; Tomlinson family.; Tucker family.
Persons:
Barnes, Margaret W.; Brown, Frances Bland Coalter, 1835-1894.; Brown, Henry Peronneau, 1831-1894.; Bryan, Fanny T.; Coalter, John, 1769-1838.; Coalter, St. George Tucker, 1809- 1839.; Coalter, Maria Rind, d. 1792.
Components List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1791-1920. (Box 1-2)
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "B", 1791-1920. (Box-folder 1:1-18)
    - Last Name - Barnes, 1861-1880, n.d., 22 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Margaret W. Barnes, Ellwood, to Fanny Bland Coalter Brown, one dated 30 May 1861 and another dated 13 January 1880, and 19 with n.d.
      Also, one, n.d., to Thompson [Brown].
    - Last Name - Braxton, 1848-1882, n.d. (Box-folder 1:2-9)
      - Bettie H. Braxton, Chericoke, to her aunt and sisters, 1851-1882, n.d., 12 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      - Betty Braxton, Chericoke, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1848-1854., 13 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      - Betty Braxton, Chericoke, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, n.d., 9 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      - Bunny [Braxton?], Chericoke, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1850-1851, n.d., 6 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      - Charles Braxton, n.p., to his aunt [Fanny?], 1878-1879., 4 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:5)
      - Lucy Tomlin Braxton, Lower Bremo and Baltimore, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1854 and n.d., 7 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      - Virginia C. Braxton, n.p., to her sister Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1859-1882., 9 ALsS and 2 ANS. (Box-folder 1:7)
      - V. C. Braxton, n.p., to her sister Fanny (Coalter) Brown, n.d., 11 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      - V. C. Braxton, n.p., to "Dear John," n.d., 1 ALS. (Box-folder 1:8)
      - F.C. Braxton, n.p., to "My Dear Aunt," n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      - Fanny Braxton to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 8 April [1851]., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      - Mary T. Braxton to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 14 June 1861., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      - T.[?] Braxton, Chericoke, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 26 March 1879., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      - Wm. P. Braxton, Oak Spring, to Fannie, 11 January 1858., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
      - [?] to his mother Mrs. Virginia C. Braxton, 7 February 1882., ALS. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Last Name - Brown, 1827-1905, n.d. (Box-folder 1:10-16)
      - Fanny Bland (Coalter) Brown, "Stanley," to H. Peronneau Brown, April-October 1858., 9 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:10)
      - Fanny Bland (Coalter) Brown to her son, husband, and "Peggy" Barnes, 1869-1875., 6 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      - Fanny Bland (Coalter) Brown to "Ginny," 30 May 1892., ALS. (Box-folder 1:11)
      - H. Peronneau Brown, n.p., to Fanny Bland (Coalter) Brown, 1861-1879., 8 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:12)
      - J.T. Brown, McBreary's, to his father Henry Brown, [1821?]., ALS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      - Henry Brown, Bedford, to his son John T. Brown, 18 July 1827 and 30 May 1829., 2 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:13)
      - List of furniture belonging to John T. Brown, n.d., Ms. (Box-folder 1:13)
      - Mary Southall Brown to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1858-1885, n.d., 21 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:14)
        Four letters have no date.
      - J. Thompson Brown to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 16 March 1858., ALS. (Box-folder 1:14)
      - J. Thompson Brown, 1880-1896., 5 AlsS. (Box-folder 1:15)
        J. Thompson Brown, Charlottesville and "Brierfield," Bedford County, Virginia, to his mother, 1880-1881, his wife, 1896, and a signed picture of a home [Brierfield?].
      - J. Thompson Brown to the Rev. W. H. Milton, the Rev. John J. Lloyd, and Mr. J. Edward Cole, 8 August 1905., TLS. (Box-folder 1:15)
      - Cassie Tucker Brown, n.p., to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, n.d., 4 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:16)
      - Dave Tucker Brown, n.p., to Mama, n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 1:16)
      - Mary Wilicox Brown, n.p., to Aunt Fanny, n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Last Name - Bryan 1855-1883, n.d. (Box-folder 1:17)
      - Fanny T. Bryan, "Casey's Point" and "Eagle Point," to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1855-1862., 8 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:17)
        Letter of 10 March 1859 mentions fire at the College of William and Mary.
      - Georgia Bryan, "Eagle Point," to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 8 January 1858., ALS. (Box-folder 1:17)
      - Joseph Bryan, n.p., to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 6 December 1883., ALS. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Last Name - Beale, 1858, n.d., 2 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Lucy C. Beale, Fredericksburg, Virginia, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 19 February [1858?] and 21 April [?].
    - Last Name - Beasley, 1878-1881., 2 ALsS. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Wm. Beasley, Petersburg, Virginia, to "Mrs. Brown," 5 October 1878 and 29 September 1881.
    - Last Name - Begg, 26 January 1896., ALS. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Janet Begg, Bedford Springs, to Cassie Tucker Brown.
    - Last Name - Bland, 12 June [18]75., ALS. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Fanny Bland, Queen's Hotel, Queenstown, Ireland, to Mrs. Brown.
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "C", 1829-1900. (Box-folder 2:1-3)
    - Last Name - Carmichael, 17 December [18]75., ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      F. T. Carmichael to Fanny [Coalter Brown].
    - Last Name - Carrington, 25 March 1879., ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Susan Carrington, n.p., to Fanny [Coalter Brown].
    - Name - Catty [?], 8 September [?]., ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Catty [?], "Otter," to Cousin Fanny.
    - Last Name - Cocke, 1880 and n.d., 6 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      L. W. and Lelia B. Cocke to Fannie.
    - Last Name - Coleman, 16 February 1900., ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
      G. P. Coleman, Richmond, Virginia, to J. Thompson Brown.
    - Last Name - Coalter, 1851-1900, n.d. (Box-folder 2:2-3)
      - John Coalter, "Walnut Hill," to his sisters and Annie, 1869-1882., 4 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - St. George Coalter, University of Virginia and Virginia Military Institute, to his sister, 31 January 1860 and 7 July [?]., ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - French exercise paper, 17 June 1854., Ms. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - V. B. Coalter, Richmond, Virginia, to Fannie B. Coalter, 8 March 1853 and n.d., 2 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - Fannie B. Coalter, Chatham, to her aunt, 15 March 1851., ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      - St. George Tucker Coalter, Chatham, to Miss Judy H. Tomlin, 1828-1829 and 1839., 20 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:3)
      - Judy H. Tomlin to St. George Tucker Coalter, n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Judy H. Tomlin later married St. George Tucker Coalter becoming Judith Harrison Tomlin Coalter.
      - Elizabeth T. Coalter Gordon, "Elwood," to Judy H. Tomlin, 8 September 1839., ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "D", 1857-1887, n.d. (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Last Name - Dallam, 1857-1861 and n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Betty B. Dallam, Baltimore, Maryland, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown.
    - Last Name - Donnan, 15 February 1887 and 7 July 1881., ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Sallie A. Donnan, Petersburg, Virginia, to "My dear friend."
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "I-G", 1859-1882, n.d. (Box-folder 2:5-6)
    - Last Name - Irvine (Box-folder 2:5-6)
      - L. T. (Brown) Irvine ["Aunt Lockie"], Otter Hill, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown, 1859 and n.d., 24 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:5)
      - L. C. Irvine, "Buffaloe," to Mrs. Brown, 12 November [?]., ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      - M. Irvine, n.p., to "My dear friend," n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Name - "Gay" [?], 1881-1882., 3 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      "Gay" [?], near Richmond, Kentucky, to "Ma" and Aunt Fannie.
    - Last Name - Ginnan, 1861, n.d., 2 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:6)
      G. B. Grinnan, Brampton, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown.
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "J-L", 1857-1896, n.d. (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Name - Jenny [?], 4 October 1859, n.d., 2 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Jenny [?], "Stanley," to Fanny (Coalter) Brown,
    - Last Name - Lacy, 18 July 1857., ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Betty C. Lacy, Eliwood, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown.
    - Last Name - Lancaster, 26 February 1896., ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Willie C. Lancaster, n.p., to "Cassie."
    - Name - "Lizie," n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      "Lizzie," n.p., to "Aunt Fannie."
    - Last Name - Lee, 15 June [?]., ALS. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Lizzie Lee, "Bremo," to Fanny.
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "M", 1855-1894, n.d. (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Last Name - "Aunt Mary," 12 October 1894., 8 ALS. (Box-folder 2:8)
      "Aunt Mary," University of Virginia, to Thompson [Brown].
    - Last Name - McIlwaine, 25 June 1855., ALS. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Josie McIlwaine, Petersburg, Virginia, to Fanny (Coalter) Brown.
    - Last Name - Morton, 1853-1881, n.d. (Box-folder 2:8)
      - J. L. Morton, Farmville, to Fannie B. Coalter, 2 August 1856., ALS. (Box-folder 2:8)
      - Mattie Morton, "Buffaloe," to Fannie B. Coalter, 3 December 1853., ALS. (Box-folder 2:8)
      - Sallie Hope Morton [?], Rockbridge Baths, Virginia, to Mrs. Brown, 20 July 1881., ALS. (Box-folder 2:8)
      - Marie Morton, Richmond, to Fanny, 1857, n.d., 9 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "P-R" 1791-1900, n.d. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Last Name - Page, 1876-1880. (Box-folder 2:9)
      - Charlie Page, Cary's Brook, to "Cousin Fanny," 27 July 1876., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      - D.B. Page, University of Virginia, to "My dear Bland," 22 March 1880., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Last Name - Randolph, 6 July 1895., TLS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      A.M. Randolph, Casanova P.O., Virginia, to F. Saunders.
    - Last Name - Rind, 29 April 1791., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Maria Rind, n.p., to John Coalter.
    - Last Name - Roberts, 14 July 1900., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Susan N. Roberts, Wady, Virginia, to J. T. Brown.
    - Last Name - Robinson [?], n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      F. B. R. [Frances B. Robinson?], n.p., to Alice Browne. Mrs. Edwin (Frances B.) Robinson and Alice Brown were sisters of John Thompson Brown (1802-1836).
  - Author's first or last name begins with - "S-Y", 1870-1903, n.d. (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Last Name - Shepperson, 10 January 1870., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      John G. Shepperson, n.p., to Fanny (Coalter) Brown.
    - Last Name - "Susie," 1878-1879, n.d., 5 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      "Susie," n.p., to "Dear Aunt F.," Virginia, and Uncle.
    - Last Name - Teates, 2 May 1898., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      W. W. Teates, Evington, Virginia, to John Thompson Brown.
    - Last Name - Tucker, 1878-1903., 5 ALsS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Members of the Tucker family including JR., Dallas, D. H., and Bev to cousins and Cassie.
    - Last Name - Womack, 4 January 1871., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Mattie Morton Womack, "Buffaloe," to Fannie.
    - Last Name - Young, n.d., ALS. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Fannie Braxton Young, West Brook, to Fannie.
  - Miscellaneous letters and other materials, n.d. (Box-folder 2:11-13)
    - Miscellaneous letters, mostly unidentified, including Henrietta, n.p., to Fannie Bland Coalter (c/o Rev. Moses Hoge, Richmond), n.d., ALsS. (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Miscellaneous notes, bills, receipts, school reports, etc. of the Brown family, n.d. (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Fragments of letters, n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
  Series 2: Photographs
- Photographs (Box-folder 3:1)
  Photographs of Jefferson Davis and Bruton Parish Church, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  Series 3: Printed Material
- Printed Material, 1827-1906, n.d. (Box-folder 3:2-3)
  - Norfolk & Western timetable, May 1906. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - The self-acting cow-milker, ca. 1878. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - John Wanamaker catalog of books, 1899. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - List, clerical and lay delegates Diocese of Southern Virginia convention, Portsmouth, 1897. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - "Fun for the million" - American News Co., 1866. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Speech of John Thompson Brown, 1833. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Speech concerns the state of relations between US, and South Carolina.
  - Small Broadside "J. T. Brown" announces to citizens of Harrison he will not be a candidate for the legislature, March 15, 1830. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Original is located in the Rare Books Department, Virginia Collection, Swem Library. Call Number: F247 H3B72 RBVA
  - Addressed to "Fellow Citizens," signed by J. T. Brown with copy of legislative act, March 14, 1829., 4 page leaflet. Photostats. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Original is located in the Rare Books Department, Virginia Collection, Swem Library. Call Number: F247 H3B71 RBVA
  - To the people of Harrison County, signed by John Thompson Brown, February 9, 1827., 20 page booklet. Photostats. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Original is located in the Rare Books Department, Virginia Collection, Swem Library. Call Number: F2k7 H3B74 RBVA
  - To the people of Harrison, signed Jno. Tho. Brown; report of committee and copy of bill, n.d., 18 page booklet. Photostats. (Box-folder 3:3)
    Original is located in the Rare Books Department, Virginia Collection, Swem Library. Call Number: F2k7 H3B73 RBVA
  Series 4: Newspaper Clippings
- Newspaper Clippings, 1836-1911. (Box-folder 3:4-9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1836-1843., 191 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1899-1911., 26 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Bedford papers, 1911., 8 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Roanoke Times, 1911., 13 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Richmond News Leader, 1911., 19 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch, 1911., 16 items. (Box-folder 3:9)